



SUMMARY

Cognitive scientist with a research focus on language development. Solid background in formal linguistics and familiar with NLP tasks. 5+ years of experience in experimental designs and data analysis, using a combination of research methods (behavioral tasks, corpus analysis, eye-tracking, neuro-imaging etc.). Proficient in R and Python.

EDUCATION

Johns Hopkins University		
Ph.D. in Cognitive Science	2019 - 2022	
Research focus: language acquisition, theoretical syntax, psy	ycholinguistics	
M.A in Cognitive Science	2018 - 2019	
Truman State University		
B.S. in Psychology and Cognitive Science, Minor in Statistical Metho	ods. Valedictorian. 2013 - 2017	

RELEVANT WORK EXPERIENCE

NLP Consultant, IDX INSIGHTS – contract

2020 – present

- Advise and assist the client with the use of NLP techniques (e.g., sentiment analysis) to predict market changes.
- Label & analyze linguistic data; verify, synthesize & summarize results to generate reports and research papers.

Graduate Student Researcher, Language Acquisition Lab, Johns Hopkins University

2018 - present

- Analyze text from multiple corpora to identify syntactic and pragmatic patterns of linguistic items.
- Conduct experiments to investigate cognitive and linguistic factors that influence language development.
- Conduct speech-perception and speech-production experiments to provide insights into the syntax-pragmaticsphonology interface. Computed models to classify linguistic variants based on prosody properties.
- Received a fellowship for using multi-disciplinary approaches in research. Published 3 papers, 4 conference talks.

Human Factors Engineer, INSULET CORPORATION – intern

6/2021 - 9/2021

- Created and conducted studies to support device design optimization and identify potential use errors.
- Authored and edited engineering documentation using cognitive and linguistic principles to ensure optimal users' understanding and processing.
- Provided research and design inputs related to human perceptual and cognitive capabilities to inform design and contribute to the verification and the validation of devices.

Lab Manager, Language Acquisition and Brain Lab, University of Delaware - full-time

2017 - 2018

- Administered a number of cognitive and language assessments to clinical and non-clinical populations.
- Used a combination of research methods (eye-tracking, EEG, fMRI, and behavioral experiments) to study the brain organization of language development and the visual-audio interface of language processing.
- Built the lab's online experimental platform. Designed and programmed 4+ experiments in JavaScript and Python. Established and wrote 80% of the lab's analysis protocol.

Statistical Consultant, CENTER FOR APPLIED STATISTICS & EVALUATION – part-time

2015 - 2017

- Provided assistance with research design, data collection, and data analysis for multiple clients.
- Example project: Designed survey questions and led focus groups to help clients understand the prevalence of writing anxiety, thus enabled them to successfully create a diagnostic tool.

APA Summer Research Scholar, TEXAS A&M UNIVERSITY – *internship*

6/2016 - 8/2016

- Conducted research on the aging brain using meta-analysis. Published 1 paper in *Human Brain Mapping*.
- Used brain stimulation (tDCS) and neuro-imaging (fMRI) to study how the brain changes over time.

SKILLS

Programming: Python, R, JavaScript, Stan

Research methods: Experiments, computational simulation, linguistic analysis, eye-tracking, neuro-imaging

Foreign language: Vietnamese

SELECTED AWARDS

•	Science of Learning Fellowship for multidisciplinary approaches in studying cognition	2020 - 2022
•	LSA Committee on Ethnic Diversity in Linguistics grant	2020
•	Dorothy Pearson Foundation Scholarship for outstanding students in Statistics	2016
•	Harold L. Hess and Ozella M. Hess Foundation Scholarship for academic excellence	2015
•	President's Honorary Scholarship for outstanding incoming students	2013
•	President's List x 8 semesters	2013 - 2017

RELEVANT COURSEWORK

Linguistics: Computational Linguistics; Computational Psycholinguistics; Intro to Human Language Technology; Language Acquisition; Syntax; Semantics; Machine Translation;

Cog. Science: Human & Computer Cognition, Cognitive Psychology, Language & the Mind, Developmental Cognitive Neuroscience, Cognitive Development, Cognitive Science; Language & Advertising

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Full list available here.

Nguyen, A., & Wilson, C. (2021). Learning the surface structure of wh-questions in English and French with a non-parametric Bayesian model. Proceedings of *the Society for Computation in Linguistics*, Vol. 4, Article 47.

Weng, Y.L, **Nguyen, A.**, Ryskin, R., & Qi, Z. (2020). Prediction and sentence ambiguity resolution: A simultaneous eye-tracking and EEG study. Poster at *33rd Annual CUNY Human Sentence Processing Conference*, Amherst, MA.

Nguyen, A., & Legendre, G. (2020). Testing syntactic simplicity: wh-in-situ vs. fronted wh-questions in L1 acquisition. Talk at *Many Paths to Language, Max Planck Institute Conference*, Nijmegen, The Netherlands.

Nguyen, A., Howe, W., & Legendre, G. (2020). Prosody as the main cue to differentiate wh-in-situ questions in acquisition. Talk at the *18th Old World Conference on Phonology*, Eivissa, Spain.

Schneider, J., Weng, Y., Kozloff, V., **Nguyen, A**., & Qi, Z. (2019). Neural sensitivity to speech distribution information underline statistical learning. Poster presented at *Neurobiology of Language*, Helsinki, Finland.

Qi, Z., **Nguyen**, **A**., Ozernov-Palchik, O., Beach, S., May, S., Arciuli, J., & Gabrieli, J.D.E. (2018). Statistical learning in reading development and reading impairment. Poster presented at *Boston University Conference on Language Development*, Boston, MA.